Guide to the Allen Johnson Correspondence Relating to the Chronicles of America Series
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Allen Johnson correspondence relating to the Chronicles of America Series
1907-1920
1916-1920
GEN MSS 1110
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.68
(16 boxes)
Correspondence of Allen Johnson concerning his editorship of the Chronicles of America Series, consisting of incoming typed and autograph letters, signed, and outgoing typescript carbons, 1916-1920. Correspondents include historians Max Ferrand, Yale University, and Nathaniel Stephenson, College of Charleston, and other authors of volumes in the Chronicles of America Series; United States Publishers' Association founders Robert Pollock Glasgow and Arthur H. Brook, Gerhard Richard Lomer, and other staff of the United States Publishers' Association; and George Parmly Day, president, and other staff of Yale University Press. Also present are memoranda and financial accounts concerning publication of the Chronicles of America Series; and correspondence about publication of Johnson's Stephen A. Douglas: A Study in American Politics (New York: The Macmillan Company, 1908), 1907-1916.
Johnson, Allen, 1870-1931
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Allen Johnson, 1925.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Allen Johnson (1870-1931) and the Chronicles of America Series
Allen Johnson (1870-1931), American historian; Yale University professor of history, 1910-1926; and editor of Dictionary of American Biography and the Chronicles of America Series. The Chronicles of America Series, a series of monographs on topics in American history, was published in fifty volumes by the United States Publishers' Association and Yale University Press, 1919-1921. Fifteen films based on monographs in the Series were produced by the Chronicles of America Picture Corporation, 1923-1924.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence of Allen Johnson concerning his editorship of the Chronicles of America Series, consisting of incoming typed and autograph letters, signed, and outgoing typescript carbons, 1916-1920. Correspondents include historians Max Farrand, Yale University, Nathaniel Stephenson, College of Charleston, and other authors of volumes in the Chronicles of America Series; United States Publishers' Association founders Robert Pollock Glasgow and Arthur H. Brook, Gerhard Richard Lomer, and other staff of the United States Publishers' Association; and George Parmly Day, president, and other staff of Yale University Press. Also present are memoranda and financial accounts concerning publication of the Chronicles of America Series; and correspondence about publication of Johnson's Stephen A. Douglas: A Study in American Politics (New York: The Macmillan Company, 1908), 1907-1916.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Incoming Correspondence, 1907-1920. II. Outgoing Correspondence, 1916-1920.
Chronicles of America series; United States -- History -- Study and teaching; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Authors and publishers -- United States; Historians -- United States -- Archives; Publishers and publishing -- United States; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Historians -- United States -- 20th Century; Brook, Arthur H.; Day, George Parmly, 1876-1959; Farrand, Max, 1869-1945; Glasgow, Robert Pollock, 1875-1922; Johnson, Allen, 1870-1931; Lomer Gerhard Richard, 1882-; Stephenson, Nathaniel W. (Nathaniel Wright), 1867-1935; United States Publishers' Association; Yale University Press
- Incoming Correspondence, 1907-1920 Bulk, 1916-1920; 1916-1920; Series I; 3.34; (8 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically by time period, and alphabetically by correspondent within each time period.
  - "A", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "B", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "C", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "D", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "E-F", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "G", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 6-10)
  - "H-J", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "K-L", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "M", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "N-O", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "P-Q", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "R", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "S", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "T-V", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "W", 1916 January-June (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Macmillan Company, 1907 October-1916 November (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Scope and Contents
    About publication of Johnson, Allen. Stephen A. Douglas: A Study in American Politics (New York: The Macmillan Company, 1908)
  - "A", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - "B", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "C", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "D", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "E-F", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "G", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 26-29)
  - "H-J", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
  - "K-L", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "M", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "N-O", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "P-Q", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "R", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - "S", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - "T-V", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - "W", 1916 July-October (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - "A", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - "B", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - "C", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - "D", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - "E-F", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 44-45)
  - "G", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - "H-J", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 47-48)
  - "K-L", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - "M", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - "N-O", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - "P-Q", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - "R", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - "S", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - "T-V", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - "W", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Copies of letters from the Yale University Press about decisions of the Yale University Council Committee on Publications, 1917 May-August (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - "A", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - "B", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - "C", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - "D", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - "E-F", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 62-64)
  - "G", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - "H-J", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 66-67)
  - "K-L", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - "M", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - "N-O", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - "P-Q", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - "R", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - "S", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 73-74)
  - "T-V", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - "W", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - "Y-Z", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - "A", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - "B", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - "C", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - "D", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - "E-F", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 82-84)
  - "G", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 85-86)
  - "H-J", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 87-88)
  - "K", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - "L", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 90-93)
  - "M", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - "N-O", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - "P-Q", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - "R", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - "S", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - "T-V", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - "W", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - "Y-Z", 1918 April-September (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - "A", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - "B", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - "C", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - "D", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - "E-F", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 106-107)
  - "G", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 108-112)
  - "H-J", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - "K-L", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 114-115)
  - "M", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - "N-O", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - "P-Q", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - "R", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 119)
  - "S", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 120)
  - "T-V", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 121)
  - "W", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 122)
  - "Y-Z", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - United States Publishers' Association, 1919 (Box 7, Folder 124-128)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also letters from Glasgow filed under "G" and letters filed alphabetically under other names
    Letters from Robert Pollock Glasgow and other United States Publishers' Association staff
  - "A", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 129)
  - "B", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 130)
  - "C", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 131)
  - "D", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 132)
  - "E-F", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 133)
  - "G", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 134)
  - "H-J", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 135)
  - "K-L", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 136)
  - "M", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 137)
  - "N-O", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 138)
  - "P-Q", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 139)
  - "R", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 140)
  - "S", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 141)
  - "T-V", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 142)
  - "W", 1919 May-October (Box 7, Folder 143)
  - "A", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 144)
  - "B", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 145)
  - "C", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 146)
  - "D", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 147)
  - "E-F", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 148)
  - "G", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 149-152)
  - "H-J", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 153)
  - "K-L", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 154)
  - "M", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 155)
  - "N-O", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 156)
  - "P-Q", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 157)
  - "R", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 158)
  - "S", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 159)
  - "T-V", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 160)
  - "W", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 161)
  - "Y-Z", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 8, Folder 162)
- Outgoing Correspondence, 1916-1920; Series II; 3.34; (8 boxes)
  - "A", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 163)
  - "B", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 164)
  - "C", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 165)
  - "D", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 166)
  - "E-F", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 167)
  - "G", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 168-170)
  - "H-J", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 171)
  - "K-L", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 172)
  - "M", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 173)
  - "N-O", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 174)
  - "P-Q", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 175)
  - "R", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 176)
  - "S", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 177-178)
  - "T-V", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 179)
  - "W", 1916 January-June (Box 9, Folder 180)
  - "A", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 181)
  - "B", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 182)
  - "C", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 183)
  - "D", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 184)
  - "E-F", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 185)
  - "G", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 186-188)
  - "H-J", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 189-191)
  - "K-L", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 192)
  - "M", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 193)
  - "N-O", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 194)
  - "P-Q", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 195)
  - "R", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 196)
  - "S", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 197-198)
  - "T-V", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 199)
  - "W", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 200)
  - "Y-Z", 1916 July-October (Box 10, Folder 201)
  - Circular letters to multiple authors, 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 202)
  - "A", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 203)
  - "B", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 204)
  - "C", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 205)
  - "D", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 206)
  - "E-F", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 207-209)
  - "G", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 210)
  - "H-J", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 211-213)
  - "K-L", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 214)
  - "M", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 215)
  - "N-O", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 216)
  - "P-Q", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 217)
  - "R", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 218)
  - "S", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 219-220)
  - "T-V", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 221)
  - "W", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 222)
  - "Y-Z", 1916 November-1917 April (Box 11, Folder 223)
  - Accounts and memoranda, 1917 May-June (Box 12, Folder 224)
  - "A", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 225)
  - "B", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 226)
  - "C", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 227)
  - "D", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 228)
  - "E-F", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 229)
  - "G", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 230)
  - "H-J", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 231-232)
  - "K-L", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 233)
  - "M", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 234)
  - "N-O", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 235)
  - "P-Q", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 236)
  - "R", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 237)
  - "S", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 238-239)
  - "T-V", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 240)
  - "W", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 241)
  - "Y-Z", 1917 May-1918 March (Box 12, Folder 242)
  - "A", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 243)
  - "B", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 244)
  - "C", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 245)
  - "D", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 246)
  - "E-F", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 247)
  - "G", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 247a)
  - "H-J", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 248)
  - "K-L", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 249)
  - "M", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 250)
  - "N-O", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 251)
  - "P-Q", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 252)
  - "R", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 253)
  - "S", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 254)
  - "T-V", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 255)
  - "W", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 256)
  - "Y-Z", 1918 April-September (Box 13, Folder 257)
  - "A", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 258)
  - "B", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 259)
  - "C", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 260)
  - "D", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 261)
  - "E-F", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 262)
  - "G", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 263-265)
  - "H-J", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 266)
  - "K-L", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 267)
  - "M", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 268)
  - "N-O", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 269)
  - "P-Q", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 270)
  - "R", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 271)
  - "S", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 272)
  - "T-V", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 273)
  - "W", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 274)
  - "Y-Z", 1918 October-1919 April (Box 14, Folder 275)
  - "A", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 276)
  - "B", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 277)
  - "C", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 278)
  - "D", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 279)
  - "E-F", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 280)
  - "G", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 281-282)
  - "H-J", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 283)
  - "K-L", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 284)
  - "M", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 285)
  - "N-O", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 286)
  - "P-Q", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 287)
  - "R", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 288)
  - "S", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 289)
  - "T-V", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 290)
  - "W", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 291)
  - "Y-Z", 1919 May-October (Box 15, Folder 292)
  - "A", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 293)
  - "B", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 294)
  - "C", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 295)
  - "D", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 296)
  - "E-F", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 297)
  - "G", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 298)
  - "H-J", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 299)
  - "K-L", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 300)
  - "M", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 301)
  - "N-O", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 302)
  - "P-Q", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 303)
  - "R", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 304)
  - "S", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 305)
  - "T-V", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 306)
  - "W", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 307)
  - "Y-Z", 1919 November-1920 May (Box 16, Folder 308)